Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. All right, so today's דף daf is
today's דף daf is י"ד, Yud Daled, we pick up five lines
from the bottom on י"ג עמוד ב' Yud Gimmel Amud Bet and
we have been discussing indirectly about a question of taking תרומה truma
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but it led to a discussion
about removing the husks
from kernels of grain and from legumes on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
where the גמרא Gemara so far has said that it's okay with
the one issue about maybe doing a large quantity, which רש"י Rashi
said was an issue of עובדא דחול uvda d'chol because it looks
like you're doing it large scale and it looks like it's for
after יום טוב. Yom Tov. And that's what we'll get to, or
by using, excuse me, not just a large quantity but using specifically
a type of a vessel like a sieve or a sifter that
was used specifically in the context of large quantity. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: כיצד מולל? Keitzad molel? How is it
that you do this מלילה, melila, that you do this removing of
the husks with your hand?
So if you take a look before we even get to the
answer, let's just look at רש"י. Rashi. כיצד מולל, Keitzad molel, two
lines from the bottom, ביום טוב b'Yom Tov on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, דאמרינן לעיל מוללין מלילות. d'aminon l'eyl molin melilot. והודאי שינוי בעי,
V'havaday shinuy ba-ei, when the גמרא Gemara said you did it, even
assuming you're not using a specialized vessel, the assumption here is that
you need to do it with some type of a שינוי. shinuy.
Why? It's a food-based מלאכה. melacha. שינוי בו מעובדא דחול. shinuy bo
mi-uvda d'chol. You have to make it somewhat different than how it
would look like during the weekday. And again, this comes to a
question about obviously by cooking we don't say that, but in some
things, maybe particularly things which sometimes will be done not in the
immediate context of preparing food in the kitchen but often will be
done in a prior pre-processing context, sometimes the חכמים Chachamim even on
יום טוב Yom Tov required a bit of a שינוי. shinuy. And
we'll be discussing that in a minute, in the next משנה mishna
as well, when it comes to the issue of grinding. Okay? So
how would you do it on יום טוב? Yom Tov? I should
mention parenthetically, תוספות Tosfot also כיצד מולל פירוש ביום טוב, Keitzad molel
peireish b'Yom Tov, says תוספות. Tosfot. ובשבת אסור למלול וכיצד, U'veShabbat assur
limlol v'cheitzad, etc., etc. Now, the רי"ף, Rif, though, by the way,
parenthetically says that we're talking even on שבת, Shabbat, that they would
even allow you to do מלילה melila on שבת Shabbat with a
שינוי. shinuy. Most ראשונים Rishonim completely reject that. You don't do, you
know, it's a מלאכה, melacha, how would we let you do it
with a שינוי? shinuy? But you should be aware that there are
some מלאכות melachot that חז"ל Chazal actually let you do connected to
food preparation on שבת Shabbat with a שינוי, shinuy, like לישה. lisha.
Like I don't know if anybody ever tried to make oatmeal on
שבת, Shabbat, which is a whole problem about like kneading, about mixing
water with some granular thing and making it like a dough-like substance,
which is what happens when you do oatmeal. And they let you
do it with a certain type of a שינוי; shinuy; you mix
them in the reverse order, you use the back of a spoon.
Since when do they allow מלאכות melachot with a שינוי? shinuy? So
somehow bizarrely, there are some food preparation מלאכות melachot that are even
allowed on שבת Shabbat with a שינוי, shinuy, a very small amount.
So the רי"ף Rif thinks מלילה melila is included, but we're going
to assume we're talking only about יום טוב, Yom Tov, and it's
also surprising that for יום טוב Yom Tov you need a שינוי.
shinuy. Okay, so כיצד מולל? Keitzad molel? How do you do it?
אביי משמיה דרב יוסף אמר: Abayei mishmei d'Rav Yosef amar: חדא אחדא,
chada achada, one finger on one finger. Like what, you do it
between two fingers like that, you rub off the husk. רב
אויא משמיה דרב יוסף אמר: Rav Avya mishmei d'Rav Yosef amar: חדא
אתרתי, chada atartei, one finger against two fingers, a little easier. רבא
אמר: Rava amar: כיון דמשני, keivan d'meshani, since you're doing it in
a different way, אפילו חדא אכולא, afilu chada akula, even your thumb
against all of your fingers. But again, presumably that's different, I don't
know, maybe you normally do it between the palms of your hand,
maybe you would do it not with your hands at all. Okay,
כיצד מנפח? keitzad minapeiach? Now you've got the husk off, how do
you wave it or blow it in order to sort of remove
the husks, the chaff, from the mixture? It's no longer physically attached;
this is now a type of a בורר. borer.
So אמר רב אדא בר אבא אמר רב: amar Rav Adda bar
Abba amar Rav: מנפח מקשרי אצבעותיו ולמעלה. minapeiach mikishrei etzba'otav u-l'ma'ala. You
hold the thing, the kernel, what you've just separated—now you have the
kernel and the husk in your hand and you hold them both
at the tips of your fingers and you wave or something, you
blow. Okay, but while it's there, not like you don't collect it
all in the palms of your hand.
Is that what you usually do, you put it in your palms?
I don't know. Or you put it in a vessel and you
sift it with a vessel. מחכו עלה במערבא, Mach-chu alei b'ma-arava, they
laughed on this in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. כיון דמשני, keivan d'meshani,
once you're doing it in a different way, אפילו בכולא ידא נמי.
afilu b'chola yada nami. Even with your whole hand, you don't have
to hold it just at the tips of your fingers. אלא אמר
רב אבא בר אלעזר: ela amar Rav Abba bar Alazar: מנפח בידו
אחת ובכל כחו. minapeiach b'yado achat u-v'chol kocho. So you have it
in one hand, again presumably not in both hands, but you hold
it in one hand
and you wave or you blow with all of your strength. But
again, as opposed to maybe putting it in some type of a
sifter. So there we're introducing the idea that there could be things
that are related to יום טוב Yom Tov and even so require
some degree of a שינוי. shinuy. And רש"י Rashi says the reason
is because of a concern of עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. But what
exactly falls in that category is not clear. For now, as I
said, we will assume it means things that evoke or can sometimes
be done in a pre-processing out of the kitchen large-scale production. Okay,
that'll be relevant as we continue on. Yes?
Is מנפח minapeiach the same as זורה? zoreh?
That's a good point.
זורה... zoreh... Yeah, but that's different. That's you throw it up and
the wind does it.
This
is like you blow with your mouth.
Well, they could have, but that might be that would be a
real מלאכה melacha you wouldn't allow. And again, I don't think we're
talking about that's something you do with wheat. This is maybe, I
mean, maybe you could in an industrial already, it's
usually on that level. Exactly. And this is also done, right, this
is, you know, this is, right, this is small scale with your
hands. It might also not be limited to the case of the
wheat, but you're right, at a large scale you would do it
by by doing זורה, zoreh, by throwing it up and having the
wind blow it away. Let's take a look now at the
משנה. Mishna. בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, so it's a perfect
segue, this discussion about doing, removing the husks and a type of
a דש, dash, and as we see that it's allowed on יום
טוב Yom Tov but certain concerns of certain degrees of שינוי, shinui,
perfect segue to the משנה Mishna that now discusses the issue about
grinding spices on יום טוב. Yom Tov. בית שמאי אומרים: Beit Shammai
omrim: תבלין tavlin if you have spices נידוכין במדוך של עץ, nidochin
b'madoch shel etz, you grind them with a wooden pestle. A pestle
is the thing you pound with, as opposed to a stone one
which would be the normal one, so you do a little bit
of a שינוי. shinui. והמלח v'hamelach and salt, which we we demand
even a greater שינוי shinui for, which we'll see why in a
minute. בפך b'pach you do it in a, not with a, here
the ב bet means in a, pottery mortar, in a pottery container.
So that's even a bigger שינוי. shinui. ובעץ הפרור u'b'etz haparur
or you use the you use the back the back hand the
back of a spoon of a wooden spoon, not even a pestle.
So you do even a bigger שינוי shinui with salt. ובית הלל
אומרים: u'Veit Hillel omrim: No. תבלין נידוכין כדרכן, tavlin nidochin kedarkan, normal
spices you don't need a שינוי shinui at all. במדוך של אבן.
b'madoch shel even. Normal spices you don't need a שינוי shinui at
all. Again, remember, it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, so why not? צורך
אוכל נפש, tzorech ochel nefesh, freshly ground spices, you can use your
normal stone mortar and pestle. והמלח v'hamelach salt does need a bit
of a שינוי, shinui, but that's only one level down. Not you
made it two levels down. So that's במדוך של עץ, b'madoch shel
etz, there you would use a a wooden pestle and not a
stone one. Okay. So let's take a look what this is about,
why you need a שינוי shinui and why spices are different than
salt. דכולי עלמא מיהא, d'kulei alma miha, the גמרא Gemara says everybody
agrees nonetheless, מלח בעיא שינוי melach ba'ya shinui that מלח melach does
require some degree of a שינוי. shinui. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why?
I mean, right, it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's מלאכת אוכל נפש.
melachat ochel nefesh. Freshly ground spices, why should you need any שינוי?
shinui? רב הונא ורב חסדא, Rav Huna v'Rav Chisda, so it's a
debate of רב הונא Rav Huna and רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. חד
אמר chad amar כל הקדירות כולן צריכין מלח ואין כל הקדירות צריכין
תבלין. kol hakedeirot kulan tzrichin melach v'ein kol hakedeirot tzrichin tavlin.
All all dishes need salt. They don't need other spices. Right? There's
a reason why salt is the one type of a thing that
we do salt and pepper, but anyway, the one spice that's always
on the table. Right? All right, we'll talk about pepper in a
minute. All all dishes need salt and therefore you should have known
from before יום טוב Yom Tov you would need salt. There's no
good reason why you left it to יום טוב Yom Tov to
grind your salt. Okay and therefore and people by the way nowadays
we all buy the table salt, you don't appreciate why you would
need to grind salt, but you know you can see there are
these things that you get these like big salt chunk crystals and
they actually have salt grinders like they have pepper grinders. Okay. So
you should have realized you needed salt and therefore if you didn't
didn't take care of it before יום טוב, Yom Tov, we're going
to demand a bit of a שינוי shinui on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Now again that is a little strange because do we say
that by other things? Do we say like, oh since you knew
you were going to have to cook your chicken if you want
to cook it on יום טוב Yom Tov you have to do
it with a שינוי? shinui? So again, when they demand a שינוי
shinui is not always so clear. But again these are things that
often are done not in the immediate context of the eating, but
sometimes a little bit you know in a pre-processing stage so that
might be also a little thing pushing us to a שינוי. shinui.
So since you could have taken should have taken care of it
before יום טוב, Yom Tov, you're going to have to do a
שינוי shinui on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. And what about other spices though?
Other spices you don't know you would need them. Okay, that's one
answer. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, the other one says כל התבלין
מפיגי טעמא. kol hatavlin mifihei ta'ama. All other spices if you do
it ahead of time, the pungency abates a little bit. It's not
as sharp. Right? Right? Right? המלח אינה מפיגה טעמה, v'hamelach eina mifiha
ta'ama, but salt if you do it ahead of time there's no
loss, so it won't it won't lose its its sharpness and therefore
you should have done it beforehand. Okay, another reason to do it
beforehand. Not just you should have anticipated, but there would have been
no downside of taking care of it beforehand as opposed to other
things. Right? Restaurants they come around freshly ground black pepper, so obviously
there's a חידוש chidush about it being freshly ground. It's going to
be a little bit sharper, much better. Okay, but salt you should
have. So two explanations why you should have done it beforehand, but
there's different reasons and it makes a difference which reason you emphasize.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו mai beinaihu what would be
a case that would be a difference between these two approaches?
איכא בינייהו ika beinaihu the difference would be דידע מאי קדירה בעי
למשלי. d'yada mai kdeira ba'ei l'mishlei. You know what dish you're planning
on making on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And you know you're making
a dish that I don't know you're going to be needing some
pepper and you're going to be needing some some garlic and who
knows what else. And therefore if the point was you should have
you knew ahead of time and you could have planned for it,
then we won't let you grind those spices on יום טוב Yom
Tov because you knew ahead of time what dish you were making
and you should have taken care of it before יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But if it's because the pungency will be weaker, then you're
entitled to wait, and therefore you can do it on יום טוב
Yom Tov itself, even though you knew you were going to need
it. That would be if you emphasize, that would be a difference.
אי נמי, Inami, here's another difference. דמורקא, Demorika, if you're using saffron.
Apparently saffron does not lose its pungency, so says רש"י. Rashi. I
haven't tested it, and therefore even if you're using
saffron, even if the issue is losing its pungency and you wanted
to use saffron, well, you should have taken care of all your
saffron grinding beforehand. But if the issue is you didn't know you
were going to need it, so you weren't thinking before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you were going to need saffron. So those, that's a
difference. Okay, so it would be important to know how we פוסקין,
poskin, because based on how we פוסקין poskin of these two reasons
will determine which spices you need a שינוי shinuy for and which
spices you can always do the normal way. Yes.
Saffron, what you would be doing is you'd be taking the plant...
No,
don't grind saffron.
They put it in the threads.
They come in little tiny...
No, the threads are like are from
a flower.
All right, so I have no idea then. Does what, but does
it translate מוריקא Morika saffron? Because that's what רש"י Rashi said.
Yeah, the Steinsaltz clearly says it's Crocus sativus. Okay, saffron flower.
I don't know. I don't know what to tell you.
I don't know what to tell you about the saffron because...
All right, you got me. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel. Says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of
שמואל. Shmuel. כל הנידוכין, Kol hanidochin, so according to this, by the
way, you should realize that in the process of giving an explanation
of why salt is different, it resulted in saying that there will
be some other spices will also demand a שינוי shinuy for when
they fall into the salt category, which was not פשט pshat in
the משנה. Mishnah. פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah is all other
spices you're off the hook. According to this, once we've explained why
salt is different and we say well, some other cases you might
have other spices that are similarly require a שינוי. shinuy. Let's see
now what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel. כל הנידוכין
נידוכין כדרכן ואפילו מלח. Kol hanidochin nidochin kedarkon va'afilu melach. Not only
can you do normal spices the normal way without the distinction she
said before, but even salt you can do the normal way and
you don't have to do a שינוי. shinuy. So the גמרא Gemara
says: והאמרת מלח בעי שינוי? Ve'ah amarta melach ba'i shinuy? But you
said, and yet you said, the משנה Mishnah said מלח melach needs
a שינוי? shinuy? הוא דאמר כי האי תנא. Hu de'amar ki hai
tanna. No, he holds like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי מאיר: Amar Rabbi Meir: לא
נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על כל הנידוכין שנידוכין כדרכן ומלח עמהן.
Lo nechelku Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel al kol hanidochin shenidochin kedarkon u'melach
imahen. Says רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, they did not debate that all
spices can be done the normal way including
salt with them. With them meaning not necessarily you're grinding them together—who
wants to mix your spices like physically in the same at the
same moment—but it means you're sitting yourself down and you're grinding all
the spices you're going to need for the meal. And salt is
one of those spices. So you have five spices you're grinding, you
can do the other spices normal way and once you're doing them
the normal way you can do the salt the normal way. It's
sort of like before, remember when we talked about delivering gifts and
the תרומה terumah together with the other gifts to the כהן, Kohen,
that somehow you can bundle it together. Even בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
even בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees to that. לא נחלקו, Lo nechelku,
where am I? אלא על הדוכה בפני עצמה, Ela al hadocha bifnei
atzma, if all you're doing is just salt. You're sitting yourself just
to do just salt. שבית שמאי אומרים מלח בפח ובעץ פרור לצלי.
SheBeit Shammai omrim melach b'pach u'v'etz parur litzli. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says salt by itself you need to have a
שינוי, shinuy, you need to use a
pottery vessel and the back of a spoon, or maybe means or
the back of a spoon, and only a little bit, only the
amount of salt you would use for roasting, not like a lot
of salt that you would use when you're salting it so much
to get out the blood because you're planning on cooking the meat.
אבל לא לקדירה, Aval lo l'kdeira, not the amount of salt you
would make for salting meat for a pot.
So if you needed it for your meat...
Yeah, I guess you'd have to do a little at a time.
ובית הלל אומרים, U'Beit Hillel omrim, so that's an extra חומרא chumra
than the משנה. Mishnah. But that's only by salt, that's the only
thing they're demanding. ובית הלל אומרים בכל
דבר. U'Beit Hillel omrim bechol davar. בית הלל Beit Hillel says with
anything. So the גמרא Gemara says: בכל דבר סלקא דעתך? Bechol davar
salka deitach? Literally with anything? Meaning what, you can use like something
מוקצה muktzah to grind? So it's a funny place to go. אלא
אימא לכל דבר. Ela eima l'chol davar. You can grind your salt
for any purpose to any degree for any purpose and again without
any restrictions. So therefore, what שמואל Shmuel is saying is according to
this ברייתא, braita, בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
are just debating salt, and according to בית הלל Beit Hillel even
salt doesn't require any שינוי. shinuy. So this is going to be
an interesting question, which way do we פוסקין, poskin, that even salt
doesn't require a שינוי shinuy or like the earlier approach where some
of the other spices, if you knew you were going to need
them or they wouldn't lose their pungency, might require a שינוי? shinuy?
So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. אמר ליה רב אחא
ברדלא לבריה. Amar lei Rav Acha Bardala livrei. רב אחא ברדלא Rav
Acha Bardala said to his son: כי
דייכת אצלי אצלויי. Ki daichat atzli atzluyei. When you grind, and we're
going to see in a minute it means when you grind salt
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, lean the vessel. Do a bit of
a שינוי. shinuy. You know, you don't have to use a different
vessel, you don't have to use wood instead of stone, but just
don't do it directly like perpendicular. Lean it a little bit at
an angle so it's not completely the normal way. ודוך, V'duch, and
then and then grind. רב ששת שמע קול בוכנא. Rav Sheshet shama
kol buchna. רב ששת Rav Sheshet on יום טוב Yom Tov heard
the sound of like the grinding of a mortar and pestle. אמר
האי לאו מגבאי דביתאי הוא. Amar hai lav migabai d'veitai hu. Ah,
that sound, that's definitely not coming from my house. I know in
my house I set down the rule, no grinding on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So the גמרא Gemara says, how do you know that
that's a problem? ודילמא אצלויי אצלי, Vedilma atzloyei atzlei,
maybe it is coming from his house, but they're doing it at
an angle since you said that was okay? So no, דשמעי דהוה
צליל קליה, Deshomei dehavei tzalil kalei, they heard that it was a
very pure sound, like the type of sound that makes by hitting
down perpendicular, not at an angle. ודילמא תבלין הוה, Vedilma tavlin havae,
but maybe it was, you know, other spices which you're allowed to
grind, you know, why are you so sure that they're not? The
only problem would have been salt, how do you know it was
salt maybe it was other spices? No, תבלין איבוכי מנבח קליה, Tavlin
ivuchei minavach kalei, תבלין Tavlin when you make the, when you grind
it, it makes more, literally, a bark sound, like I don't know,
some sort of as opposed to a crushing sound, a more popping
sound, and therefore he knew it was salt, he could tell by
the sound that it was salt, and it was salt being done
the normal way, and he knew in his house they would never
grind salt the normal way. So look what the גמרא Gemara has
come to, right? The גמרא Gemara basically is following the thrust of
שמואל. Shmuel. Normal spices, no problem, like we don't make any distinctions
like we made before, which is consistent with the משנה. Mishna. And
even salt at the most what we're saying is it needs to
be done at an angle, but other than that even salt can
be done with the normal types of a vessel. Okay, now, how
do we פסקן pasken before we move on? So if you take
a look at תוספות, Tosafot, right, this is a very important question.
Can you go ahead and grind fresh pepper on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Okay, so let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. איכא בינייהו
דעידו מיקדמי בי בישולי. Ika beina'ehu de'idu mekaddmei bei bishulei.
So it says דלישנא קמא בעו שינוי ולישנא בתרא לא בעו שינוי.
de'lishna kama ba'u shinui velishna batra lo ba'u shinui. So אי נמי
בהאי שאינו מפיג טעמו ולא ידע לישנא בתרא צריך שינוי ולישנא קמא
לא צריך שינוי. Ei nami behei she'eino mefig tamo velo yada lishna
batra tzarich shinui velishna kama lo tzarich shinui. So he's dealing with
the two different approaches, whether you could have anticipated it or is
it a type of spice that loses its pungency. And now what's
the הלכה? halacha? He says, ופסק רי שיש לאסור בכל ענין. U'pasak
Ri she'yesh le'esor bechol inyan.
You should forbid both cases, either if you could have anticipated or
if it's a type of spice that doesn't lose its pungency. The
only thing you'd be able to grind is you couldn't have anticipated
it and it doesn't lose its pungency. Okay, why? דאף על גב
דבשל סופרים הלך אחר המקל, De'af al gav de'veshel sofrim halacha achar
hamaykel, even
though you're lenient by rabbinics, so we should be go the lenient
approach.
He
says, הלא לכל אחד ואחד יש קולא וחומרא מכל צד דדינה לחומרא.
Halo lechol echad ve'echad yesh kula ve'chumra mikol tzad d'dina l'chumra. He
says how could you be lenient here because there's no one lenient
opinion. Each side has leniencies and stringencies. So since there's no way,
and if you're lenient both ways, then you're just rejecting the two
opinions. So there's no way to be lenient here, so we have
to be מחמיר machmir both ways. Now, that's a little funny, but
I should say because it's getting to be ערב פסח Erev Pesach
that there's a great example of this by פסח Pesach where the
גמרא Gemara has a ספק safek do you lean, talking about leaning
and the lenience but I didn't mean that, but talking about leaning,
leaning and pounding, do you lean during the first two כוסות kosos
or the last two כוסות? kosos? So the גמרא Gemara says, well,
since we don't know you have to lean for all four. So
the רא"ה Ra'ah says whatever happened to the principle of ספק דרבנן
לקולא? safek derabbanan l'kula? He says no, but if you do ספק
דרבנן לקולא safek derabbanan l'kula you won't lean for any.
So therefore you've got to lean for all four. So he's saying
you can't say ספק לקולא safek l'kula here because then you'll reject
all the decisions, so we have to be מחמיר machmir for both.
That's his first approach which doesn't, which I don't know. So then
he says, but then he goes on and then he starts pulling
back. He says, ומיהו שום מותר לטחנם ביום טוב בלא שינוי. U'mihu
shum mutar l'tachnan b'Yom Tov b'lo shinui. First of all garlic you
can because שמתקלקלים ביותר. she'mitkalkelim b'yoter.
Those, maybe even if you could have anticipated it, those really lose
its pungency and that would certainly be allowed. Okay and then he
has another reading. And then he says like
this: ומיהו מהאי פסקא לא נפיק לן מידי. U'mihu me'hai piska lo
nafik lan midi. He says really this whole גמרא Gemara is not
relevant, these distinctions could you have anticipated, would it lose its pungency?
דהא קיימא לן כשמואל בסימוך. De'ha kaima lan ke'Shmuel besimuch. In the
end we go like שמואל Shmuel דכל הנידוכין נידוכין כדרכן dechol haniduchin
niduchin k'darkan that everything is normal and maybe the only thing is
בר מלח דאיכא דצריך
אצלויי דרך שינוי מעט. bar melach d'ika d'tzarich atzloyei derech shinui me'at.
At most maybe salt which needs a little bit of a שינוי.
shinui. Okay, so and if you keep on going says the רי"ף
Rif פסקנים paskens that way, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda פסקנים paskens that
way, רב יהודה האי גאון. Rav Yehuda Hai Gaon. Skipping down a
few lines, וכן יש מנהג הלכה למעשה דהך מילתא תלוי באשלי
רברבי. Vechen yesh minhag halacha l'ma'aseh d'hach milta taluy b'ashlei ravrevei. This
is the practice, in practice we grind spices on יום טוב Yom
Tov without a שינוי, shinui, maybe at most salt we do differently.
Okay, ומכל מקום, u'mikol makom, so it's great now I can have
my freshly ground pepper. No, ומכל מקום u'mikol makom even though all
spices are fine except maybe salt with a שינוי, shinui, אסור לטחון
פלפלין בריחיים שלהם. assur l'itchon pilpilin b'reichayim shelahem. You can't use peppers
in their grinder משום דמיחזי כעובדא דחול כשתוחנין בריחיים שהן מולינתא בלע"ז.
mishum d'michzi k'uvda d'chol k'she'tochnin b'reichayim shehen molinta b'la'az. That looks like
עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. אבל במדוך של אבן מותר לדוכן בלא שינוי.
Aval b'madoch shel even mutar l'duchan b'lo shinui. But in a normal
mortar and pestle it's fine. Now why is that עובדא דחול? uvda
d'chol? And let me just finish and then I'll go back to
it. Okay, he says like this...
and then he says even if you say you can't do pepper
but if you don't know... whatever... okay fine.
He says like this, two lines from the bottom, I just want
to read you a nice poetic ending, he says like this, he
says, דקיימא לן דכל הנידוכין נידוכין כדרכן, de'kaima lan dechol haniduchin niduchin
k'darkan, if you say you could do all spices. some other way,
יש להתיר אפילו כי ידעה מעיקרא דבעי לבשולי yesh lehatir afilu ki
yad'ah me'ikara d'ba'ei levashulei then you could do it even if you
knew what type of thing you'd be cooking, you knew to anticipate
it. If we say like שמואל, Shmuel, it doesn't matter, it's always
allowed. ואפילו לא מפיק טעמו, va'afilu lo mafik ta'amo, so even if
you knew, even if it doesn't lose its pungency, according to שמואל,
Shmuel, no problem, you can always do it the normal way. It
says והמחמיר לדוכן מערב יום טוב הרבה ביחד, vehamachmir ledochan me'erev Yom
Tov harbeh beyachad, if you're want to be מחמיר machmir and do
it all ahead of time,
ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, יתברך באלוהים ובשם המפורש yitbarech belohim
uveshem hameforash to be blessed by God and by the ineffable name.
Anyway, all right, very interesting, you know, poetic ending there. But the
הלכה למעשה halacha lema'aseh you really can grind spices on יום טוב
Yom Tov that you want to use for, you know, that they
should be, you want to use for the dishes that you're making
on יום טוב Yom Tov with the possible issue of עובדא דחול.
uvda d'chol. Now, this idea that using a pepper grinder is עובדא
דחול uvda d'chol is also for example another hot take, it
looks like עובדא דחול.
uvda d'chol. Right. Another example of that comes up in a case
by שבת Shabbos about grating cheese with a cheese grater which is
brought down by one of the בעלי התוספות Ba'alei Hatosfos as עובדא
דחול. uvda d'chol. Now how do you define what עובדא דחול uvda
d'chol means? So there are some contemporary פוסקים poskim and you will
find this pretty much throughout the שמירת שבת כהלכתה Shemiras Shabbos Kehilchasa
that translates עובדא דחול uvda d'chol as, he doesn't say this literally
but this is effectively how he translates it as, as like modern
labor-saving devices. So any type of a, you know, of a modern
kitchen appliance all of a sudden becomes עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. I
don't know if he even goes so far to apply it to
like a peeler, but pretty much like any types of those modern
labor-saving devices. It's crazy. Why is doing the less work on שבת
Shabbos and not exerting the same amount of effort like עובדא דחול?
uvda d'chol? Maybe it just evokes a world of I don't know
modernity and technology. But רב משה Rav Moshe completely rejects this. And
רב משה Rav Moshe says the reason these are identified as עובדא
דחול uvda d'chol are they're the type of vessels like רש״י Rashi
said before by using the סיסטרא systra by using the סיסטרא, systra,
these are types of vessels that are often used in a large-scale
context and in a context that's done not in the immediate preparation
of food in the kitchen but the large-scale preparation that's done before
it gets to your kitchen. Those type of vessels that evoke that
type of a, you know, of a preparing of the food, that's
עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol.
Because you're one in your home it's a lot smaller than one
you get in a restaurant.
Right, exactly. So it means depending on, so you see תוספות Tosfos
says if you use a mortar and pestle, you ask me, pounding
peppercorns with a mortar and pestle is a lot more effort than
one of those hand grinders. But so it'd be interesting to know
what type of grinder he's referring to. But it is not that
all convenient labor-saving devices are עובדא דחול, uvda d'chol, if anything you
might say the opposite. So the reality is that if you have
a small home grinder, you should be totally able to grind fresh
pepper on יום טוב Yom Tov and to grind fresh spices on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's only one possible difference of the salt
would require a שינוי. shinuy.
What is the concept of מחזי כעובדא דחול mechazi ke'uvda d'chol similar
to the category of a כלי המיוחד
לכך?
kli
hamiyuchad lekach?
כלי המיוחד לכך kli hamiyuchad lekach for like what context you're talking
about?
לשבת leShabbos in terms of שבת. Shabbos.
Oh you mean like for בורר? borer? No, that's, no, that's more
about in order to define something not as בורר borer you have
to make it דרך אכילה derech achilah which means you can't use
a specialized כלי. kli. But that's different. That's when you're starting with
a, that's to get it out of a מלאכה melacha category. Here
it's okay because it's, it's אוכל נפש ochel nefesh and it's יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So it's, I mean it's similar concerns about how
a כלי kli redefines something but it's coming from a different perspective.
But I'm also always concerned with this מחזי. mechazi. In other words
how much can a, you didn't build much on the מחזי. mechazi.
In other words how much is it really
the מלאכה melacha we all know it's not but it's מחזי. mechazi.
Yeah that's true, there's a difference between it genuinely being עובדא דחול
uvda d'chol and looking like עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. You know it's
true, I don't exactly if I knew exactly what עובדא דחול uvda
d'chol is maybe I could tell you exactly the line between them.
But I do think that point about, you know, that רב משה
Rav Moshe makes again, it is true, I'll tell you, check שמירת
שבת, Shemiras Shabbos, he'll tell you there's a lot of things you
can't do, you know, because he just once it uses an appliance
he'll call it עובדא דחול uvda d'chol which רב משה Rav Moshe
says is like completely wrong. Since when is labor-saving device עובדא דחול?
uvda d'chol? Yes.
Since we've been talking now here about spices and
minutes ago we were talking about meat
and grinding meat. So does the same logic that we just concluded
with here also apply to
meat?
Grinding meat doesn't even enter into a מלאכה melacha category really. What
do you mean like making like making hamburger meat?
Taking a steak and grinding it into meat.
Grinding it? Yeah. So that would just that wouldn't even be a
מלאכה melacha issue but that would be an עובדא דחול uvda d'chol
issue. But that would be a good example like how many houses
have one of those meat grinders, right?
And
not everybody's clear...
Well not in my house. So again I guess it depends, you
know, but that would be an interesting example. Okay.
I've never heard of anybody grinding their own sausage.
This just decided to start working, so I'm just going to start
recording now. Okay, yeah.
Rabbi, I just have a quick question.
Wait, Michael raised his hand.
Yes. So basically, I just want to understand, so
regular
spices, how are they usually done? So we're putting it in your
mortar and pestle, that's not עובדא דחול? ovda d'chol?
No, because it can be. עובדא דחול ovda d'chol does not mean
just the normal way you do it. I mean, you know, why
isn't cooking עובדא דחול? ovda d'chol? הטפאה אינו מבשל, Hatapah eino mevashel,
but you put on the fire. עובדא דחול ovda d'chol means specifically
according to Rav Moshe, evoking, you know, the more, I would say
like industrial, I don't know if industrial is the word, but yes.
According to תוספות, Tosafos, it doesn't say it. It's a question how
do you interpret תוספות, Tosafos, right? He says somehow this particular type
of a grinder is עובדא דחול. ovda d'chol. What makes it עובדא
דחול? ovda d'chol? But presumably, it's the more the way, what?
That thing is עובדא דחול. ovda d'chol. But but using a pestle
and
Correct, right, and the way Rav Moshe explains is your mortar and
pestle is the way you prepare spices in the home, whereas these
other types of things are the way that you would do it,
you know, pre-house, the way it would be processed out there in
the fields or in the industry, you know, in the process of
getting it to the store. Okay, let's now continue. י"ד, Yud Daled,
we pick up with תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, about ten lines from
the bottom.
I just want to ask you a phrase.
Yeah. What's באשלי רברבי? b'ashlei ravrevei? Oh, like in like on big
trees, like just suspending yourself on a sure, right, oh, so many
you have a strong support. It's an idiom. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, okay, about ten lines from the bottom, י"ד. Yud Daled. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: אין עושין טיסני ein osin Tisni on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you cannot make טיסני, Tisni, which is some type of
a of a grain-based dish. Okay,
how does it does it say anything there about what טיסני Tisni
is?
Grits made from wheat kernels that are split into quarters.
Grits made from wheat kernels that are split into quarters. Okay, so
anyway, it's a grain-based dish that requires a lot of effort, a
lot of טירחא tircha in doing it. So again, even though even
though you can do אוכל נפש ochel nefesh on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, they wanted to limit the amount of טירחא, tircha, so you
cannot make טיסני. Tisni. Well, טוחן tochen isn't the problem because it's
יום טוב, Yom Tov, okay, but you can't make it because of
the effort. But one minute, now we're going to get to the
next line: ואין קוצצין במכתשת, ve'ein kotzin b'machteshes,
but you also can't grind the wheat in a grinder. Right, now
that sounds like categorically you can't because of a טוחן tochen concern,
but you know, why should that be different than grinding spices, which
is normally טוחן, tochen, I don't know if we mentioned that, but
the normal מלאכה melacha of grinding spices is טוחן, tochen, grinding, okay,
but we allow it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So here, because
we're dealing with wheat, so what's the story? You just can't make
this dish that requires a lot of effort or you can't grind
it at all? So that's what the גמרא Gemara asks: תרתי? tarti?
How can you say both? Make up your mind. Either it's the
problem with the dish or it's the problem with grinding wheat that
somehow that's a bigger problem. So the גמרא Gemara says fine: הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
here's what we mean. מה טעם אין עושין טיסני, mah taam ein
osin Tisni, why can you not make this טיסני? Tisni? לפי שאין
קוצצין במכתשת, lefi she'ein kotzin b'machteshes,
because it's not really about the טיסני Tisni because fundamentally you can't
grind with this מכתשת. machteshes. Okay, maybe that's also some type of
עובדא דחול, ovda d'chol, maybe those are more done things that are
not sort of like home-based and so on and large scale. So
now we're going to see one minute, let's see the גמרא Gemara
continues. Let's let me say ואין קוצצין במכתשת, ve'ein kotzin b'machteshes, just
tell me don't use a grinder, why you have to give me
the example of this dish? אי תנא אין קוצצין במכתשת, ei tana
ein kotzin b'machteshes, if you had said that, הוה אמינא, hava amina,
I would have said הני מילי במכתשת גדולה, hani mili b'machteshes gedola,
that's only a large grinder, again because the large more is this
עובדא דחול ovda d'chol as we've been talking about.
אבל במכתשת קטנה, aval b'machteshes ktana, a small like little home-based one,
אימא שפיר דמי, eima shapir dami, maybe it would be okay. קמשמע
לן, kamashma lan, so it says both. It says don't do it
and then it extends it, so it's a little bit redundant to
underscore that you cannot use any type of a wheat grinder, even
a small one. Okay, which is again a little bit funny and
therefore the גמרא Gemara says and is going to pull back on
that because again why mention particularly one particular type of a dish?
גמרא Gemara says: והתניא, ve'hatanya, but we taught in a ברייתא: braisa:
אין קוצצין במכתשת גדולה, ein kotzin b'machteshes gedola, you can't use a
big grinder, אבל קוצצין במכתשת קטנה, aval kotzin b'machteshes ktana, you can
use a small wheat grinder.
So if you take a look by the way at רש"י, Rashi,
why is that different? So רש"י Rashi says five lines from the
bottom: אבל קוצצין בקטנה aval kotzin b'ktana דהוי כלאחר יד de'havei ke'lochar
yad דאינה אלא לתבלין. de'eina ela l'tavlin. A small one is normally
used for spices, so it's doing it with a שינוי. shinuy. Again,
not exactly clear why you need a שינוי, shinuy, but again, presumably,
a big one is this עובדא דחול ovda d'chol concern again. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אה, ah, אבל קוצצין במכתשת קטנה. aval kotzin
b'machteshes ktana. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, כי תניא מתניתין מכתשת גדולה תניא.
ki tanya matnisin machteshes gedola tanya. Fine, you're right, we retract our
previous position and we said don't make this, don't make what was
it, טיסני, Tisni, because you don't grind with a grinder, we mean
don't make טיסני Tisni at all even if you're using a small
grinder, because that's טירחא, tircha, that's a lot of effort, and don't
use a big grinder, but a small wheat grinder for other things,
that would be okay. Just one minute. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא
Rava says: לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא לן
והא להו, ha lan v'ha lehu, it's the difference between us and
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now what's the difference between us and ארץ
ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? As we're going to see. See in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael they had they had slaves or servants or slaves and
therefore although it's funny the גמרא Gemara often mentions slaves of the
house of the ריש גלותא Resh Galuta who were often very not
scrupulous about הלכה halacha but here we're sort of saying that the
larger problem in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael society. And therefore for them
they when we said you can't use even a small one, that
was our interpretation earlier, that would be for בני ארץ ישראל bnei
Eretz Yisrael that if they use a small we let you use
a small one they'll claim they used the big one. But here
in בבל Bavel where we're not afraid of that type of impropriety
or lack of scrupulousness, we allow people to use a small one.
And now we're going to have a story that supports it. רב
פפי איקלע לבי מר שמואל Rav Papi itkla le-vei Mar Shmuel so
Rav Papi came to the house of Mar Shmuel. אייתו ליה דייסא
Aitu lei daysa they brought him some oatmeal on יום טוב Yom
Tov freshly ground oatmeal. ולא אכל Ve-lo achal he refused to eat
it.
ודילמא במכתשת קטנה עבדוה Ve-dilma be-machteshet ktana avduah maybe they used a
small grinder which we said was okay and it's even and certainly
okay in בבל? Bavel? דחזא דהוה דייק טפי De-chaza de-hava dayek tfei
no no no he saw that it was very very thin it
was done to the quality that you would only do in a
big grinder. Okay. ודילמא מאתמול עבדוה Ve-dilma me-etmol avduah maybe it was
prepared yesterday? דחזא דהוה קליף צהרי De-chaza de-hava klif tzaharei they saw
that it was like a very bright you know the the flakes
were very bright fresh very freshly ground oatmeal he could tell. ואיבעית
אימא Ve-iba'it eima so therefore
okay so therefore he saw that it was done in a big
grinder and he refused to do it because you can't use a
big grinder. ואיבעית אימא Ve-iba'it eima and if you want you could
say שאני בי מר שמואל דאיכא פריצותא דעבדי Shani bei Mar Shmuel
de-ika pritzuta de-avdei the house of Shmuel is different because the servants
there or the slaves there
are not scrupulous and therefore it's like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
therefore he felt that in Shmuel's house they shouldn't be using even
a small grinder because again of the concern about whether people are
going to be scrupulous or not say they use the big one
and claim they've used a small one. But the basic הלכה halacha
is you're allowed to use a small one not a big one
and again what's the concern with the big one presumably again this
issue of עובדא דחול. uvda de-chol.
Yes I have a question remember when we were first getting confused
do we say לישה ואילך lisha ve-eilach isn't that a ירושלמי Yerushalmi
תוספות Tosafot brought that you spoke of this before lunch?
Yeah so so that is an excellent question and the principle of
לישה ואילך lisha ve-eilach what Michael is saying is he's reminding us
of a תוספות Tosafot a quoted ירושלמי Yerushalmi that said that said
that the only מלאכות melachot that you can do on יום טוב
Yom Tov it's not everything you can't go out and start harvest
you know your wheat and cutting down your wheat only things that
are from the type of adding the water onwards and these things
the grinding and the sifting and the and the threshing that we've
been discussing are things that precede לישה. lisha. So that's an excellent
question and you could try to claim well maybe that's why we're
introducing these ideas of שינוי shinuy but it doesn't work because we
said for example spices could be כדרכו ke-darko right? So although the
מולל מלילות molel melilot we said was with a שינוי shinuy but
spices were כדרכו. ke-darko. So it's an excellent question and it forces
most to say like obviously that that principle is not absolute and
there's a lot of discussion about that but I will tell you
again and this conceptually works very nicely why should we say only
from לישה lisha onwards? Why is the moment of kneading different than
the threshing and the you know the harvesting and the grinding and
the winnowing and all of that? Well the basic logic of the
difference is that all that other stuff happens before you get it
to the house whereas לישה lisha are the home-based מלאכות. melachot.
So so the same with grinding. There's the grinding of turning wheat
into into into flour which is not done in the house. There's
the grinding of spices and there's the grinding of taking wheat kernels
and making you know oatmeal you know which is done in the
house. So it could be rather than a categorical distinction of מלאכות
melachot one through twelve no and like thirteen through thirty-nine yes or
whatever it is you know the difference is again whether home-based or
or not home-based and that seems to be a very good way
of categorizing the differences and that also explains the concerns of עובדא
דחול. uvda de-chol. עובדא דחול uvda de-chol is it's true you are
grinding the spices in the home but if you're or but if
you're using a vessel that evokes the type of grinding that is
outside of the home that's the and the problematic one that's the
type of vessel you can't be using. So it's an excellent question
the easiest way of understanding it is not particularly categorical מלאכות melachot
it's mostly like the locus of the מלאכה melacha yes.
So there had been times in history where most wheat was ground
in homes although obviously it wasn't here.
Really? I mean didn't they have these big water mills and whatever
that the ground the wheat in?
Yes but not everywhere. And you can and you can actually buy
home wheat grinders and lots of people actually like to do that
because they think they get fresher I see. So the my question
is is this a categorical distinction or might it change depending
on
what you have at home... Well what we're seeing right now is
if you use a small מכתשת machteshet you can do it. Now
רש״י Rashi says a small מכתשת machteshet is made for spices right?
But it's not so clear from the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
could be talking about a home-based small... all wheat grinder, a grinder
that's made for wheat, but it's made for the small-scale grinding that
you do at home. Okay. But it's a good question.
Here's a picture of what we're seeing.
Excellent. Okay. Alright, so let's continue, but I think you get the
conceptual categories. Let's look now at the next משנה. mishna. הבורר קטניות
Haborer kitniyot so we're doing, we're going through the מלאכות melachot here.
We've done דשה dasha which is like right, the threshing essentially, the
removing of the husks. We've done טוחן, tochein, the grinding, and now
we're going to do בורר, borer, all of these are classic מלאכות
melachot as Michael pointed out, they normally are in the field with
the grain, but also they take place in the home at different,
on different contexts. And the same is with בורר. borer. What's the
story with בורר borer on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Let's take a
look at the
משנה. mishna. הבורר קטניות ביום טוב. Haborer kitniyot be-Yom Tov. You are
separating out your legumes, again we had this before, you remove the
husks and then you have to separate, after you've separated the thing
from the husks, they're mixed together and then you have to separate
them out. So בית שמאי אומר, Beit Shammai omer, בורר אוכל ואוכל.
borer ochel ve-ochel. You separate out the food and you eat it,
meaning you do it like on שבת, Shabbat, you do אוכל מתוך
פסולת, ochel mitoch psolet, you focus on the food and then you
eat it immediately. So that's considered דרך אכילה, derech achila, right? So
that's basically how you're allowed to do that type of thing on
שבת. Shabbat.
So for בית שמאי Beit Shammai it's not clear whether יום טוב
Yom Tov is any different than שבת. Shabbat. You focus on the
food and you eat it. But בית הלל אומר, Beit Hillel omer,
בית הלל Beit Hillel says, בורר כדרכו. borer kederko. No, you can
do like you would normally do בורר, borer, which maybe means you
remove the פסולת, psolet, not the food.
ובחיקו, Uve-cheiko, you do it either on like your chest, meaning like
in your lap. בקנון ובתמחוי, Bekanon uvetamcho, you can use even a
vessel or a funnel, אבל לא בטבלא ולא בנפה ולא בכברה. aval
lo betavla velo benafah velo bichvara. You cannot use, and this you
might remember we had the same thing before when we were talking
about getting the wheat removed from the husks, you cannot use like
a big sifter or a colander or whatever, a vessel made specifically
for בורר, borer, for sifting. But basically he says other than using
a vessel made specifically for sifting, you can do בורר borer the
normal way you would do it. So again, and maybe the whole
problem of this vessel is like we've been saying before, maybe it's
this עובדא דחול uvda dechol concern. Fundamentally, בורר borer is okay, just
don't use a very professionalized vessel for it which makes it much
more עובדא דחול uvda dechol rather than focused on the immediate home
use. רבן גמליאל אומר אף מדיח ושולה. Rabban Gamliel omer af mediach
veshola. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says you can even wash them off
and then scoop it from the top, like you put it in
water and the chaff falls to the bottom and the other stuff
on the top and you scoop it off from the top. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תניא, Tanya, ותנא ברייתא. utanah
Baraita. אמר רבן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Gamliel, במה דברים אמורים כשאוכל מרובה
על הפסולת. bamei devarim amurim keshe-ochel merubeh al hapsolet. When is it
that
בית הלל Beit Hillel says that you remove the פסולת? psolet? When
there's more food than פסולת, psolet, so removing the פסולת psolet is
the, you're removing the minority. אבל פסולת מרובה על האוכל, Aval psolet
merubeh al ha-ochel, if there's more פסולת psolet than there is אוכל,
ochel, the food is the minority and the waste is the majority,
then דברי הכל נוטל את האוכל ומניח את הפסולת. divrei hakol notel
et ha-ochel u-maniach et ha-psolet. You remove the אוכל. ochel. So you
focus on what is lesser rather than what's larger, presumably because of
the issue of as we're going to see, not a definition of
בורר borer which again is not seen as a problem, but as
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, a question of טרחא. tircha. You
want to do it in a way that minimizes the effort. So
you always remove, no, שבת Shabbat is totally different. This is יום
טוב, Yom Tov, where fundamentally it's מותר. mutar. But you have to
do it in a way which focuses on the minority thing because
that minimizes the טרחא. tircha. And we'll see the גמרא Gemara will
make it clear in a minute, I'll get back to you in
a second. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says פסולת מרובה על האוכל, psolet merubeh al
ha-ochel, one minute, if there's more chaff, more waste than there is
food, מי כאן דשרי? mi ka man de-sharei? How can, who would
allow it? Why not? So what רש''י Rashi says is that if
this thing is majority chaff, it's מוקצה, muktzeh, right? There's a little
food buried in it, but it's mostly chaff,
then the whole thing as a totality is looked at as not
food, as מוקצה, muktzeh, who can move it? No, לא צריכא, lo
tzricha, you need it for the following case. דנפיש בטרחא וזוטר בשיעורא.
De-nafis betircha vezutar beshiva. It's true, there's a minority of it in
quantity, so fundamentally it's food, it's not waste, it's not chaff. The
amount of פסולת psolet is the minority. But if you were to
focus on the פסולת psolet to remove it, it would be more
effort to remove the פסולת psolet based on how they're connected, it's
usually easier to remove one rather than the other. So based on
the particular way they're mixed and connected, it's more effort to remove
the פסולת psolet than the אוכל, ochel, and in that case, you
remove the אוכל. ochel. So the basic point is, according to בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, you always do it the way which minimizes the
טרחא. tircha. The key in the גמרא Gemara is that phrase at
the end, דנפיש בטרחא, de-nafis betircha, which means again that the principle
is there is not a בורר borer concern. It's יום טוב. Yom
Tov. The concern is just do it in a way that minimizes
the טרחא tircha and don't use a professional vessel. And those are
the two concerns that we continue to have by יום טוב, Yom
Tov, even when you're doing מלאכות melachot of food preparation. Number one,
like we talked before about this, you know, crushed wheat dish, you
shouldn't have too much טרחא, tircha, that's an issue, we don't want
you to have to go to be a lot of effort on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. And number two, the professional vessel because of
the עובדא דחול. uvda dechol. Those are the concerns. But again... Look
at this, you really can on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you're there,
you're chopping your whatever, you know, your red peppers and you got
the seeds and whatever. If it's יום טוב, Yom Tov, you basically
don't have to worry about בורר. borer. If again it's that house-based
type of a preparation. All you have to do is do it
in a way that minimizes, that minimizes the effort. Now as far
as שבת Shabbos is concerned it has nothing to do with minimizing
the effort. It's about defining it as דרך אכילה. derech achilah. So
what defines it as דרך אכילה derech achilah is you take the
food and you put the food into your mouth. And so it's
always about doing the אוכל מתוך פסולת. ochel mitoch psoles.
Oh okay fine I didn't hear, yes. By שבת Shabbos it just
starts about the אוכל. ochel. Yes.
He gives the example of קטניות. kitniyos. Or like pieces of or
kernels of grain.
You can have more פסולת psoles than you have אוכל. ochel. It's
a one-to-one correspondence. It's like, right, every grain, every piece of barley
has like a husk, right?
Yeah,
we actually
just
ate edamame that was cooked in the pod this past שבת Shabbos
and right at the table we squeezed out the beans to eat
and we had a lot of pods.
That would be a good example, קטניות kitniyos would be an example
where there's much bigger pods than there are seeds. I will remind
you that
רש״י Rashi on יא עמוד ב yud aleph amud bais that we
learned on שבת Shabbos where it says don't use a sifter. רש״י,
Rashi, I'll just read you the רש״י Rashi there, it's three lines
from the bottom, you don't have to turn to it. יא עמוד
ב, yud aleph amud bais, רש״י Rashi says דמיחזי כמאן דעביד לצורך
מחר שאין דרך לעשות בכלים הללו אלא הרבה. dimichzi k'man d'avid l'tzorech
machar she'ein derech la'asos b'keilim hallalu ela harbeh. So again that is
the other concern. It's sort of עובדא דחול uvda d'chol by using
certain types of vessels that are done large scale not for immediate
use and that's the עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. Those are the two
dominant concerns even by מלאכות melachos that are allowed because they're food
based. רבן גמליאל אומר אף מדיח ושולה. Rabban Gamliel omer af madiach
v'sholeh. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says you can submerge it in water
and then scoop off the stuff on the top. תניא tanya we
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק כך היה
מנהגן של בית רבן גמליאל, amar Rabbi Elazar berabi Tzadok kach haya
minhagan shel beis Rabban Gamliel, this was the practice in the house
of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. שהיו מביאים דליים של עדשים, shehayu mevi'im
d'li'im shel adashim,
they would have a bucket filled with lentils. ומציפים עליו מים, umatzifim
alav mayim, and they'd have the water, you know, put water on
it, the water would be on top of the lentils. ונמצא אוכל
למטה פסולת למעלה, venimtza ochel lemata psoles lemala, and the chaff would
rise to the top and the food would be on the bottom.
גמרא Gemara says והתניא איפכא, vehatanya ipcha, one minute, the ברייתא braisa
says the opposite, that the food would be on the top and
the chaff would go to the bottom. לא קשיא הא בעפרא הא
בגילי. la kashya ha b'afra ha b'gilei. The difference is are we
talking about dirt
which is
heavier and that would stay at the bottom, or are we talking
about like the type of
chaff which is light and that would float to the top. Okay
next משנה. mishna. So now we've covered a lot of מלאכות. melachos.
We've covered
דש, dash, right, we've covered טוחן tochen and we've covered בורר borer
and the common denominator is just do it in a way that
doesn't have a lot of טרחא tircha and do it in a
way that does not use certain vessels which evoke עובדא דחול uvda
d'chol but not all vessels, not right, you can use your mortar
and pestle. You can use, you know, labor-saving devices, just not ones
that evoke that whole large scale עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. Next משנה.
mishna. בית שמאי אומרים אין משלחים ביום טוב אלא מנות. Beis Shammai
omrim ein meshallchin b'yom tov ela manos. So now we get back
to דרבננס. derabbunans. אין משלחים ביום טוב אלא מנות, ein meshallchin b'yom
tov ela manos, you can only send if you're sending somebody a
gift on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you can only send them a
מנות. manos. Like משלוח מנות איש לרעהו, mishloach manos ish l're'eihu, something
that is basically ready to be eaten. Not something that requires preparation
even preparation that could be done on יום טוב. Yom Tov. ובית
הלל אומרים u'Beis Hillel omrim and בית הלל Beis Hillel says, okay,
because
of
what, because of you as a recipient.
I don't know, it just seems like you don't want to, you
know, have to send something that might not, if somebody even though
technically somebody could cook it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you send
somebody a raw fish they weren't planning on cooking it and maybe
it's a מוקצה muktzah issue or it's a טרחא tircha issue, I
mean not really מוקצה muktzah but you know.
It could be clothes, something to be worn?
Okay, clothes would be probably included in that. Things that could be
readily worn, readily used are okay but not things that could not
be even if you could cook it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
ובית הלל אומרים משלחים בהמה חיה ועוף, u'Beis Hillel omrim meshallchin beheima
chaya v'of, you can even send livestock because you could always שחט
shecht it. בין חיים בין שחוטים, bein chayim bein shechutim, whether alive
or slaughtered. משלחים יינות שמנים וסלתות, meshallchin yeinos shmanim u'soltos, you could
send oil, wine and flour even though you'd have to turn the
flour into dough. It's all things that in theory you could use
even though it requires effort. וקטניות u'kitniyos or legumes. אבל לא תבואה,
aval lo tevuah, but you can't send like unground grain. Okay, that
presumably although we did talk before about a certain type of, you
know, home grinding that could be done, presumably that would be, you
know, under all normal circumstances not usable. רבי שמעון מתיר בתבואה, Rabbi
Shimon matir bitvuah, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows even that. Okay
and רש״י Rashi says because as we learned there are things you
could do, you could use a small grinder. Okay, תני רב חייא
ובלבד שלא יעשנו בשורה. tani Rav Chiya u'vilvad shelo ya'asenu b'shurah. So
even though not בסורה, b'sorah, בשורה. b'shurah. Even though we allow you
to send these types of gifts you can't. have to do it
like יעקב Yaakov sent to עשיו, Esav, גמרא Gemara doesn't say that
but to me that's what it's evoking, which is a whole line
of people bringing gifts, you know that makes it very you
know weekday-like having all these people come and deliver gifts after gifts
and so on. Also I think that some of this you have
to understand the context of Roman context of patronage and of you
know of of the giving of gifts and the receiving of gifts
like the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin talks about sometimes you know
you can מקדש mekadesh a woman by agreeing to receive a gift
from her because you know in that certain society of patronage if
you agree to receive a gift that's very sort of symbolically meaningful
and means that you're taking you know you know you're being the
patron of this person anyway so could be that that also evokes
certain types of you know more business and commercial types of of
contexts as well. Anyway רש״י Rashi says it's just making a big
production out of things which is not appropriate on יום טוב. Yom
Tov.
תנא כמוליכין למכור השוק.
Tanna kemolichin
lemakor hashuk.
A business thing?
Yeah, yes, right. That's what רש״י Rashi says, correct. רש״י Rashi says
that if you have all these people bringing gifts it looks like
it looks like you're going to sell the stuff. Okay. תני אין
שורה פחותה משלושה בני אדם. Tani ein shurah p'chusah mishloshah bnei adam.
A שורה shurah would be at
minimum three people. Two people would not be considered a row of
people bringing gifts. ובעא רב אשי, U'va'ei Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav
Ashi asks: תלתא גברי ותלתא מיני מאי? Tlata gavrei v'tlata minei mai?
Let's say you're sending with three people but each person you're sending
to bring a different gift. You know some have the עזים מאתים
izim matayim and some have the רחלים rahelim and some have the
תישים. tyashim.
So is that considered like a row because each one is bringing
something different? Maybe you look at each one individually? מאי? Mai? תיקו.
Teiku. That we don't know. All right. רבי שמעון מתיר בקטנית. Rabbi
Shimon matir b'kitnit. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows you to even send
grain. תניא רבי שמעון מתיר בקטנית Tanya Rabbi Shimon matir b'kitnit כגון
חטים לעשות מהן לודיות, kigon chitin la'asot mehen ludiyot,
חטים chitin to make from it לודיות, ludiyot, רש״י Rashi says this
is a wheat-based dish. שעורים ליתן לפני בהמתו, Se'orim litein lifnei beheimto,
barley to give to your animal. ועדשים Ve'adashim and lentils לעשות מהן
רסיסין la'asot mehen resisin which is a lentil-based dish. Okay fine. Anyway
these are things that בית שמאי Beit Shammai and even בית הלל
Beit Hillel might not allow just because it would be very unusual.
The normal use for this thing would be done would not be
would not be would not be in a way you could do
it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Yes?
There's a whole thing about in if you could explain for a
moment. There's an about receiving gifts on שבת Shabbat or יום טוב?
Yom Tov?
And normally on שבת Shabbat you're not supposed to you're not supposed
to do a קנין kinyan on שבת Shabbat but you can give
a gift on שבת Shabbat that can be used on שבת Shabbat
because it's allowed לצורך שבת, letzorach Shabbat, so that's okay. If you're
going to give something something on שבת Shabbat that you think they
won't use and won't use immediately and you want to be פרום
frum what you do is you מקנה makneh it to a third
party before שבת Shabbat before you deliver it or you give it
to them on שבת Shabbat and say I'm not being מקנה makneh
it to you yet, you can be you can take official possession
of this after שבת. Shabbat.
But generally or like after the holiday then?
Yeah. But generally the point is that if it can be used
on שבת Shabbat it's fine. Let's take a look let's take a
look at the next משנה. mishna.
משלחים כלים, Meshachin keilim, now that we talked about food let's talk
about more like non-consumables.
You can send vessels, meaning clothing, בין תפורים בין שאינם תפורים. bein
tforim bein she'einam tforim. This is according to בית הלל Beit Hillel
who has a broader allowance, whether the whether the clothes are sewn
or not sewn. So what are you going to do with not
sewn clothes? Okay we'll see. ואף על פי שיש בהן כלאים, Ve'af
al pi she'yesh bahen kilayim, even if there's שעטנז shatnez in it.
That's like wild. What are you supposed to do with שעטנז? shatnez?
והן לצורך המועד. Ve'hein letzorech hamoed. But all these things is if
they can be used for יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now if you
look at the side there's a different גירסא girsa of the משנה,
mishna, ואף על פי שאין לצורך המועד. Ve'af al pi she'ein letzorech
hamoed. Even though it's not for יום טוב Yom Tov since in
since it's even if in principle I mean even if practically it's
for to use afterwards since hypothetically it could be used now that's
sort of a different גירסא. girsa. Therefore it's allowed but we're going
to have to figure out is how could it hypothetically be used
now? Okay. But but according to the other גירסא girsa of the
משנה mishna it means even if your intention was to be used
after יום טוב Yom Tov since it's a hypothetical possibility that suffices.
אבל לא סנדל המסומר, Aval lo sandal hamesumar, not a nailed sandal
which the Rabbis forbade people to wear on שבת Shabbat and יום
טוב Yom Tov because of a certain story which we'll find out
about.
ולא מנעל שאינו תפור, Velo min'al she'eino tafur, a non-sewn shoe which
has no use at all, no even hypothetical use until you sort
of sew up the leather and so on. רבי יהודה אומר אף
לא מנעל לבן, Rabbi Yehuda omer af lo min'al lavan, even a
white shoe meaning before the leather has been blackened. משום שצריך אומן
Mishum she'tzarich uman because you need a craftsman to blacken it and
again there would be no theoretical use for this even though it's
sewn. Nobody goes out wearing white shoes and there's no theoretical use
for this. זה הכלל כל שנהנין בו ביום טוב משלחים אותו. Zeh
haklal kol she'nehenin bo beyom tov meshachin oto. Anything that hypothetically you
could benefit on יום טוב Yom Tov you can send even if
as we said before that's not your primary intention. So let's just
read a little bit about how could you theoretically benefit from these
things? בשלמא תפורים, Bishlama tforim, I understand sewn up clothes. חזו למלבוש,
Chazu lemalbush, you can wear them. שאינם תפורים She'einam tforim if they're
not sewn up נמי חזו לכסויי, nami chazu lechisuyei, you could use
it as a blanket, you could use it to cover yourself with
even if you can't wear it yet. אלא כלאים, Ela kilayim, but
שעטנז, shatnez, למאי חזי? lemai chazi? What can you use שעטנז shatnez
for? וכי תימא חזו לממחטי, Vekhi teima chazu lemitmachtei,
maybe you can use it to to sort of put under you
as a mat, so you don't wear שעתנז, shatnez, but you can
sit on it. והתניא, vehatanya, but we taught in the ברייתא, braisa,
לא יעלה עליך, lo ya'aleh alecha, בגד כלאיים שעתנז לא יעלה
עליך, beged kilayim shatnez lo ya'aleh alecha, a שעתנז shatnez garment should
not be placed upon you. אבל אתה יכול להציע תחתיך, aval atah
yakhol lehatziot tachtecha, biblically you can have it as a mat underneath
you. You're not wearing it, it's just a cushion. אבל, aval, that's
biblically. אבל אמרו, aval amru, but the sages said, אמרו חכמים, amru
chachamim, אסור לעשות כן, assur la'asos ken, you can't do it. שמא
תכרוך נימא על בשרו, shema tichroch nima al besaro, maybe a strand
will go on your flesh and it will be יעלה עליך. ya'aleh
alecha. It won't just be under you. Okay, so you can't use
it for a mat. וכי תימא דמפסיק מידי ביני וביני, vechi teima
demafsik midi beini uveini, oh
what I'll do is I'll have it as a mat below the
pillow. So it's not possible that a string will go on me
because it'll be כלאיים, kilayim, a pillow, and then my tush. So
maybe that should be allowed. And אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר רבי משום
קהלא קדישא דירושלים, amar Rabi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabi Yehoshua ben
Levi amar Rabi Yosei ben Shaul amar Rebbi mishum kehila kadisha deYerushalayim,
fascinating, רבי Rebbi in the name of the holy community of Jerusalem,
אפילו עשר מצעות זו על גב זו וכלאיים תחתיהם, afilu eser matzot
zo al gav zo vekilayim tachtehem, even ten mats stacked up, it's
like the Princess and the Pea, and the כלאיים kilayim is on
the very bottom, אסור לישון עליהם, assur lishon aleihem, they did not
let you, the rabbis once they said you can't use it as
a mat, it did not matter what the circumstances were. So we
are going to pick up with this tomorrow and find out what
possible use you could have for שעתנז shatnez on יום טוב yom
tov if not only can you not wear it but you cannot
even use it as a mat.